A Guide to the Papers of William M. Fontaine 1836-1903
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of William M. Fontaine 1836-1903
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1459
Ca. 75 items (9 Hollinger boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Archival transfer: Geology School; University of Virginia; 1942 June 18.
Biographical/Historical Information
William M. Fontaine, son of James Fontaine and Juliet C. Morris. Born 1835 in Hanover County, Virginia, died 1913 in Charlottesville, Virginia. Professor of geology at the University of Virginia, hired at the University of Virginia in 1878 as the first professor of natural history, with a $50,000 endowment from Washington philanthropist W. W. Corcoran.
Scope and Content
Included are numerous reports, notebooks, and lecture notes by UVA Professor William Fontaine and others on the natural sciences including geology, botany, and paleontology in Virginia, North Carolina, Oregon, Maryland and elsewhere. Also included is correspondence to Jedediah Hotchkiss of the United States Geological Survey on topics concerning geology in Georgia, Virginia, and Washington State as well as a diary kept by Maury Fontaine at Rochelle Farm for the period 1883-1886.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into unbound and bound volumes, with unbound materials stored first. Within the two series, materials are arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Series I: Papers of William M. Fontaine (Box 1-2)
  - "Brief Sketch of the Geology of...Region[s] Situated Between the Potomac and Rapphannock,...Petersburg to the Potomac,...the Blue Ridge..., etc." 1840 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence to William Fontaine 1899, 1902 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence to Jedediah Hotchkiss 1883, 1894 (Box 1:3)
    including oversize topographical and geology maps of Washington state compiled by Fred G. Plummer, Tacoma, Washington, 1894 (removed to OS Tray A)
  - "The Flora of the Potomac Formation in Virginia" by William Fontaine 1887 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - "Geological Formation of Va." By Wm. B. Rogers, Report from 1836, Extracts 1836 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - "Geological Survey of Washington County, Pa.," by John J. Stevenson 1875 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - "Geology and Mineral Resources of Kansas" by Robert Hay 1894 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Geology of the Younger Mesozoic Formation as Shown in the State of Virginia 1885 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - German and English Botany Notes n.d. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - German Language Notebook n.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Indian Mounds Paper n.d. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Linnaea XVIII, XIX, XXI (Black and White Plant Illustrations) 1844-1846, 1848 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Mineralogy 1879 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Miscellaneous Letters n.d., 1884-189? (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Miscellaneous Reports 188? (Box-folder 1:15-16)
  - Notes on the Geology of Virginia, Vicinity of Hanover County n.d. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Notes on the Gold Fields of Floyd and Montgomery Counties, Virginia n.d. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Kaolin of Nelson County. Letter/Notice from William Fontaine, "The Board of Visitors Desires to Form a Collection of Iron Ores of the State"
  - Notes on the Mesozoic Strata of Cumberland and the Adjoining Counties ca. 1880 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Ores of the Kentucky Tract by William M. Fontaine n.d. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - "The Potomac Formation in Virginia" by William Fontaine ca. 1888 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Report Fragment n.d. (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Report Fragment n.d. (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Report Fragment "...the East Side of the Blue Ridge" n.d. (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Report to the UVA Board of Visitors on Geological Fieldwork by William Fontaine ca. 1880 (Box-folder 2:9-10)
  - Report to the UVA Board of Visitors, Geological Work Done in May-June 1882 1882 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Tertiary Region South of James n.d. (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Younger Mesozoic Strata of Virginia n.d. (Box-folder 2:13)
- Series II: Bound Volumes of William M. Fontaine (Box 3-9)
  - Botany Notebook 1887? (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Untitled Botany and Geology Notebook 1887-1897? (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Botany Notes n.d. (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Botany Notebook n.d. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Botany Notebook n.d. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Catalogue of Cabinets of Mineralogy, Geology and Zoology offered by Mr. Henry A. Ward to the University of Virginia May 1876 1876 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Catalogue of Fossils and Minerals in Cabinet of Dr. G.A. Williams n.d. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Crater Lake Notebook n.d. (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Definition and Relations of Geology ca. 1888 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Diary of Maury Fontaine 1883-1886 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Extracts from Whymper's "Travels among the Great Andes" and Virginia Geology Notes n.d. (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Fossil Plants of the Jurassic 1886? (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Fossil Plants from the Mesozoic of Virginia n.d. (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Geological Notes, Mesozoic Notes (Various Virginia Locations) 1878-1880 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Untitled Geology Notebook n.d. (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Geology Notes n.d. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Geology Lecture Notes n.d. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Untitled Geology Notes n.d. (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Geology II n.d. (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Lecture Notes n.d. (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Lectures on Mineralogy n.d. (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Maryland Plants n.d. (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Concerning Earthquake Shocks ca. 1874 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Notes from Emmon's Geology of North Carolina ca. 1875 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Notes of a Geological Exploration...Fredericksburg to Alexandria 1884 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Notes on the Occurrence of Vespertine Plants n.d. (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Occurrence and the Relations of the Ores of Iron 1882 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Notes on...Trips to Waynesboro and James River 1883 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Notes on Virginia Geology n.d. (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Paleontological Geology n.d. n.d. (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Plants Collected from...Douglas County, Oregon n.d. (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Shell Cabinet (Inventory) ca. 1903 (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Taconic System n.d. (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Trimetric Orthorhombic or Rhombic System 1883? (Box-folder 8:7)
  - Untitled Geology Notebook n.d. (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Untitled Notes n.d. (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Untitled Notebook n.d. (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Untitled Notebook n.d. (Box-folder 9:4)
  - Untitled Notebook 1871? (Box-folder 9:5)
  - Virginia Geology Notes ("Powel's Gap to Stannardsville" [sic]) n.d. (Box-folder 9:6)